Olutomilayo Olayemi Petinrin

Github: github.com/olutomilayo

Professional Summary

I am a goal-oriented data scientist with over six years of experience in telling insightful stories with data. I am particularly drawn to high-impact fields of data science, hence my focus on Cancer research over the span of my graduate studies. Data is ubiquitous, and the methods of ploughing through it are numerous and ever-evolving. This presents a challenge that I embrace with excitement, both as a daily task and as a commitment to be on the cutting edge of the field. I am a happy learner, a keen observer and a firm believer that everything I do must be geared towards growth, contribution and impact.

EDUCATION

City University of Hong Kong, (CityU)

Kowloon, Hong Kong

Email: olutomilayo.petinrin@gmail.com Mobile: +85251619943, +2347069606278

Doctor of Philosophy - Computer Science; GPA: 3.65/4

Sept 2019 - Aug 2023

Courses: Data Mining and Warehousing, Machine learning: Application, Optimization and Complexity theory, Research Methodology

Universiti Teknologi Malaysia

Skudai, Malaysia

Master of Computer Science; GPA: 3.95/4

Aug 2016 - Dec 2017

Courses: Data Structure and Algorithms, Theory of Computer Science, Computer System and Architecture, Data Mining

Ekiti State University

Ado-Ekiti, Nigeria

Bachelor of Science - Computer Science; GPA: 4.53/5

Sept 2009 - Dec 2014

Relevant Courses: Numerical Analysis, Artificial Intelligence, Structured Programming, Application Software Development

SKILLS SUMMARY

• Languages: Python, R, JavaScript, C++ • Frameworks: Scikit, TensorFlow, Keras

• Platforms: Web, Windows, JASP, WEKA, Matlab

• Soft Skills: leadership, event management, communication for scientific and professional purposes, team building English (full professional proficiency), Yoruba (native proficiency), French (elementary proficiency) • Communication:

• Interests: cycling, swimming, hiking, badminton, table tennis

EXPERIENCE

Cornell University

Visiting Research Scholar

Ithaca, NY, USA

Sept 2022 - Feb 2023

• I am currently working on the development of machine learning methods for Cancer and Tuberculosis patient classification based on genomics and metabolomics data sets.

• I use JASP and R for statistical analysis.

City University of Hong Kong

Hong Kong

Teaching Assistant

Sept 2019 - Aug 2023

- I was in charge of labwork for the following courses: Data-Intensive Computing, Big data Algorithm & Technique, and Introduction to Computer Programming.
- I was a tutor for Introduction to Computer Science for four semesters.
- I prepared lab materials, graded tests and assignments, and attended to students' questions.

Kings University

Odeomu, Nigeria

Lecturer

Mar 2018 - Aug 2019

- I taught the following courses: Fundamentals of Data Structure & Algorithms, Computer Networks, and Object-Oriented Programming.
- I developed mid-semester quizzes, homework, and exams.
- I coordinated grading and labwork.
- I supervised two student projects.

National Institute for Educational Planning and Administration

Ondo, Nigeria

System Analyst

May 2015 - Apr 2016

- I traced and restored network disconnections in the different parastatals of the Institute.
- I tutored university interns on practical networking and web development skills.
- I was a member of the networking team that set up a computer-based test facility for almost 1000 students.

Bureau of Computer Services and Information Technology, Office of the Governor. Osogbo, Nigeria Aug 2012 - Feb 2013 Intern

- I monitored the Network Operating Center (NOC) of the State. I also traced connection loss and facilitated its
- I was responsible for constant network connection in all office ministries.
- I tutored college students on basic computer skills.

PUBLICATIONS

- Book Chapter: Petinrin, O. O., & Wong, K. C. (2021). Protocol for Epistasis Detection with Machine Learning Using GenEpi Package. In Epistasis (pp. 291-305). Humana, New York, NY.
- Journal: Liu, Z., Liu, X., Liu, F., Zhao, H., Zhang, Y., Wang, Y., Ma, Y., Wang, F., Zhang, W., Petinrin, O.O. & Yao, Z., 2022. The comprehensive and systematic identification of BLCA-specific SF-regulated, survival-related AS events. Gene, 835, p.146657.
- Journal: Petinrin, O. O., Saeed, F., Li, X., Ghabban, F. & Wong, K. C. (2022). Reactions' Descriptors Selection and Yield Estimation Using Metaheuristics Algorithms and Voting Ensemble. CMC-Computers, Materials & Continua, 70(3), 4745-4762.
- Journal: Petinrin, O. O., Li, X., & Wong, K. C. (2021). Particle Swarm Optimized Gaussian Process Classifier for Treatment Discontinuation Prediction in Multicohort Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer Patients. IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics.
- Journal: Liu, L., Chen, X., Petinrin, O. O., Zhang, W., Rahaman, S., Tang, Z. R., & Wong, K. C. (2021). Machine Learning Protocols in Early Cancer Detection Based on Liquid Biopsy: A Survey. Life, 11(7), 638.
- Journal: Ogunsina, A. A., Petinrin, M. O., Petinrin, O. O., Offornedo, E. N., Petinrin, J. O., & Asaolu, G. O. (2021). Optimal distributed generation location and sizing for loss minimization and voltage profile optimization using ant colony algorithm. SN Applied Sciences, 3(2), 1-10.
- Journal: Aghimien, E. I., Aghimien, L. M., Petinrin, O. O., & Aghimien, D. O. (2020). High-performance computing for computational modelling in built environment-related studies—a scientometric review. Journal of Engineering, Design and Technology.
- Journal: Petinrin, O. O., & Saeed, F. (2019). Stacked ensemble for bioactive molecule prediction. IEEE Access, 7, 153952-153957.
- Journal: Hameed, S. S., Petinrin, O. O., Osman, A., & Hashi, F. S. (2018). Filter-wrapper combination and embedded feature selection for gene expression data. Int. J. Advance Soft Compu. Appl, 10(1), 90-105.
- Journal: Afolabi, L. T., Saeed, F., Hashim, H., & Petinrin, O. O. (2018). Ensemble learning method for the prediction of new bioactive molecules. PloS one, 13(1), e0189538.
- Journal: Petinrin, O. O., & Saeed, F. (2018). Bioactive molecule prediction using majority voting-based ensemble method. Journal of Intelligent & Fuzzy Systems, 35(1), 383-392.
- Conference: Petinrin, O. O., Saeed, F., & Al-Hadhrami, T. (2017, October). Voting-based ensemble method for prediction of bioactive molecules. In 2017 2nd International Conference on Knowledge Engineering and Applications (ICKEA) (pp. 118-122). IEEE.
- Conference: Muniru, I. O., Shifulah, N., Petinrin, O. O., & Utama, N. P. (2017). A Digital Technology Framework for Promoting Nutritional/Health Benefits of West African Diet. In 2017 3rd International Conference on Science, Engineering, and the Social Sciences (ICSESS) Page, 29, 201.
- Conference: Petinrin, O. O., & Olatunbosun, K. (2017). Application of machine learning in prediction of bioactivity of molecular compounds: A review. Technology (ICONSEET), 2(2), 9-15.
- Conference: Olatunbosun, K., & Petinrin, O. O. (2017). Expert System for Diagnosis of Malaria and Typhoid Fever. Technology (ICONSEET), 2(44), 341-346.

Honors and Awards

Proctor

Academic Director

Deeper Life Campus Fellowship

- Outstanding Academic Performance Award, City University of Hong Kong: 2022
- Research Tuition Scholarship, City University of Hong Kong: 2020
- UGC-funded Postgraduate Studentship Award, City University of Hong Kong: 2019 2023
- Best Student Award, Faculty of Computing, Universiti Teknologi Malaysia: April 2018
- MTN Foundation Scholarship Award for Science Students: 2012 2014
- University Scholarship Award for first class students: 2011

LEADERSHIP AND VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

•	Research Education Committee, Dept. of Computer Science, CityU	Hong Kong
	Member	Sept 2021 - Aug 2023
•	Association of Nigerian Scholars in Hong Kong (ANSHK)	Hong Kong
	First female Secretary	Oct 2021 - Sept 2023
•	Navigating Hong Kong, ANSHK	Hong Kong
	Guest Speaker	2020
•	Electoral Committee, ANSHK	Hong Kong
	Member	2020
•	Electoral Committee, International Student Society (ISS-NIGERIA), UTM	Malaysia
	Member	2017
•	Annual General Meeting Committee, ISS-NIGERIA, UTM	Malaysia
	Member	2017
•	Information Communication and Technology Community Development Service G	Group Ondo, Nigeria
	Project Coordinator	2015 - 2016
_	Joint Admissions and Matriculation Board	Ondo, Nigeria

2016

Ekiti, Nigeria

2011 - 2012